Guide to the Cornwall Schools Collection 1833-1990 (Bulk 1833-1940) MS 031 MS 031 MS 031
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Schools Collection
1833-1990
, (Bulk 1833-1940)
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 031
4 linear feet (8 boxes)
This collection is devoted to Cornwall’s educational history.
Provenance
This collection was begun by Cornwall historian E.C. Starr and added onto by subsequent town historians and presidents of the Cornwall Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
At its peak, Cornwall was divided into seventeen school districts, each with its own schoolhouse. However, as the town’s population began to decline after the mid-nineteenth century, these schools closed and were eventually consolidated into the Cornwall Consolidated School in 1940. This collection contains information on all but four of Cornwall’s former school districts, as well as on general state educational requirements, various private schools that existed at one time in the community, and colleges attended by town residents. The majority of materials are related to the Second School District, which encompassed the area around Cornwall Plain.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes eight archival boxes which are devoted to district schools, private schools, universities, and general information, respectively. The exception to this ordering is the Second School District, which has two archival boxes devoted to its materials. Each of these boxes are subdivided into sections, which are arranged in chronological order, or alphabetically by teacher’s last name.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically or chonologically by topic.
The files are grouped into 4 series:
State Educational Information and District Schools
Private Schools and Cornwal Public Schools
Colleges and Universities
Miscellaneous
Cornwall (Conn.)--Education.; Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Receipts (financial records); Pamphlets; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
- State Educational Information and District Schools
  - Connecticut Common Schools
    - Annual Common Schools Reports, 1839-1841 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Circular Letter sent to common schools, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First School District
    - E.C. Starr’s notes on the history of the district, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence between E.C. Starr and Flora Wedge about district history, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Third School District
    - List of district children, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fourth School District
    - Copies of "Public Acts" of state common schools, 1846-1854 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Fifth School District
    - Ezra D. Pratt penmanship book, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Ezra D. Pratt teaching certificate, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Books listing expenses and students, 1835-1858 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Copy of annual report on common schools, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - School register, 1841 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Orders to pay teachers, 1855-1858 (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
    - Fire insurance policies, 1855-1866 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Receipts related to new schoolhouse, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
    - Receipts of E.D. Pratt, 1857-1858 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Deed from James Wadsworth, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Meeting minutes, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Copy of "Connecticut School Register", 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - List of money due, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - List of district residents, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - List of district scholars, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Eighth School District
    - Meeting minute book, 1835-1895 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Ninth School District
    - Brief sketch of district’s history, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Tenth School District
    - Copies of "Connecticut School Register", 1869-1871 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Twelfth School District
    - Record book, 1833-1890 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Deed from Noah Rogers, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - District rate bill, 1847 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - List of expenses and taxes, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Hattie Pratt teaching certificates, 1873-1874 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - Thirteenth School District
    - Meeting notes, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Notices for district meetings, 1889-1891 (Box 2, Folder 2-8)
    - School property assessments, 1890; , undated (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
    - Tax information, 1890; , undated (Box 2, Folder 12-19)
    - Rate bills, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
    - Student lists, 1890-1892 (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
    - Note sent to S.G. Patterson, treasurer, from O. Perkins, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Certification to receive annual appropriation, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Bond, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - List of expenses, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Dry goods bill from Smith Sons, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Copy of letter to New Milford Savings Bank, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - List of annual appropriation, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - List of miscellaneous costs, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Blank enumeration sheet, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Attendance sheet, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Certification of elected district officials, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Fall term report, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Attendance Record, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Index to unknown school record book, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - List of expenses, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Notes on expenses and committee members, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Possible list of students and grades, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Empty envelopes, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Fifteenth School District
    - Souvenir with photo of Alice E. Murray, teacher, and list of pupils, 1899 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Clerk’s book, 1903-1908 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Sixteenth School District
    - Copies of "Public Acts relating to Common Schools in Force in the State of Connecticut", 1860-1886 (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
    - Copies of state education laws, 1868-1886 (Box 2, Folder 47-49)
    - Description of district limits, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Seventeenth School District
    - Register of students, 1860-1862 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Map showing Cornwall schools, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - E.C. Starr notes on district boundaries, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Meeting minutes for unknown school, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Typed manuscript on school districts, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Slate book, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Second School District
    - General Expenses
      - Orders for coal, 1848-1872 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
      - Orders for firewood, 1861-1872 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      - Account with M. Beers Sons, 1857-1871 (Box 3, Folder 6-8)
      - Account with Pratt Foster, 1870-1874 (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
      - Account with Cornwall Bridge Iron Co., 1872 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Teacher Accounts
      - Darius Basler, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - A.B. Benedict, 1859 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Caroline M. Cole, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Cornelia A. Drake, 1857-1858 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
      - Lucretia J. Kellogg, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Emily F. Marsh, 1871-1872 (Box 3, Folder 20-21)
      - R.J. Miner, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
      - H.A. Munson, 1870-1873 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
      - Leonard Nickerson, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - J.H. North, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Charlotte E. Payne, 1859-1860 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
      - List of teacher wages, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Term Bills
      - Summer term bills, 1854-1860 (Box 3, Folder 32-36)
      - Winter term bills, 1854-1861 (Box 3, Folder 37-42)
    - Building Expenses
      - Contract for schoolhouse repairs, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Deed from the Pierce family to the Second School District, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Records from the construction of a new schoolhouse, 1870-1873 (Box 3, Folder 45-74)
    - Miscellaneous
      - District meeting notices, 1855-1874 (Box 3, Folder 75-93)
      - Receipts, 1855-1873 (Box 3, Folder 94-98)
      - Tax information, 1871-1874 (Box 3, Folder 99-100)
      - Expense reports, 1870-1874 (Box 3, Folder 101-104)
      - Petitions, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 105-106)
      - Warrant for unpaid debts, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 107)
      - Bills for unspecified debts, 1856 (Box 3, Folder 108-125)
    - General Expenses
      - Orders for coal, 1876-1883 (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
      - Orders for firewood, 1882-1884; , undated (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
      - Account with M. Beers Sons, 1879-1887 (Box 4, Folder 10-13)
      - Account with Pratt Foster, 1875-1877 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Account with Cornwall Bridge IronCo., 1879-1883 (Box 4, Folder 15-21)
      - Account with Smith Sons, 1882-1908 (Box 4, Folder 22-25)
      - Account with Theo. Sturges, 1904-1908 (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
      - Account with Cochrane Bros., 1889 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Account with C.E. Wilcox Son, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Teacher Accounts
      - A. Bennett, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Hattie D. Bennett, 1880-1881; , undated (Box 4, Folder 31-33)
      - S.E. Harrison, 1882-1883 (Box 4, Folder 34-36)
      - Mary Marsh, 1875-1876 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Almon Miner, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Ida Miner, 1884-1885 (Box 4, Folder 39-41)
      - Emily Nickerson, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Leonard J. Nickerson, 1879-1880 (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Mrs. John A. Page, 1881-1882 (Box 4, Folder 44-45)
      - Mrs. Porse, 1882 (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Amount paid to various teachers, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Building Expenses
      - Bills for painting schoolhouse, 1875-1887 (Box 4, Folder 48-51)
      - Repair bills, 1875-1920; , undated (Box 4, Folder 52-56)
      - Bills for fence construction, 1886-1887 (Box 4, Folder 57-58)
    - Miscellaneous
      - District meeting notices, 1875-1909; , undated (Box 4, Folder 59-85)
      - Receipts, 1875-1880; , undated (Box 4, Folder 86-89)
      - Tax information, 1878-1907 (Box 4, Folder 90-92)
      - Expense reports, 1875-1909; , undated (Box 4, Folder 93-108)
      - Bills for unspecified debts, 1875-1913, , undated (Box 4, Folder 109-121)
      - Resignation notice of J.B. Baldwin from school committee, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 122)
      - Notice of S.C. Beers’ appointment to school committee, 1878 (Box 4, Folder 123)
      - List of orders, 1883-1884 (Box 4, Folder 124)
      - Report card of Lydia Hubbard, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 125)
      - Program for closing exercises, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 126)
      - Program for play, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 127)
      - Christmas card, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 128)
      - Photocopy of class photo with explanatory letter, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 129)
      - Notes and class photograph belonging to Lydia Brewster Hubbard Wolf, undated (Box 4, Folder 130-131)
      - School journal, The Cornwall Plains School Tonic, undated (Box 4, Folder 132)
- Private Schools and Cornwall Public Schools
  - Alger Institute
    - Awards of merit given to T. Robert Baldwin, 1855 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Address given by alum, Luther H. tucker, 1861 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Cornwall Consolidated School
    - Article, "Enlarged Cornwall School Has Open House", 1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Program for graduation exercises, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Booklet, "Cornwall Consolidated School," by Mrs. Burdick’s 4th grade class, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Letter sent to Mr. and Mrs. Gannett about student honors, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Medal designed by student David Orrell, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper story on war memorial playground, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cornwall Public Schools
    - Program for Christmas pageant, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Program and ticket for play, "Goldilocks and the Bears", 1926 (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
    - Closing exercise programs, 1919-1936; , undated (Box 5, Folder 12-18)
  - The Cornwall School
    - Announcement about grand opening, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Booklet on school opening, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Catalogue, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Advertisements, , undated (Box 5, Folder 22-23)
    - Annual booklets, 1899-1903 (Box 5, Folder 24-27)
    - Issues of The Cornwall School Quarterly, 1899-1900 (Box 5, Folder 28-36)
    - Programs for closing exercises, 1900-1901 (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
    - Program for celebration of Washington’s birthday, 1900 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Image, 1901 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Application for admission, 1904 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Program for Red Cross benefit play, 1919 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - The Foster School
    - Program for school entertainment, 1903 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Informational booklet, 1904-1905 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Program for school play, 1906 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Glen Home
    - Pamphlet for Glen Home, "A Select School for Young Ladies", undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Housatonic Valley Institute
    - Annual reports, 1886-1897 (Box 5, Folder 47-52)
    - Programs for entertainment, 1888-1897 (Box 5, Folder 53-59)
    - Poster and program for play, "David Copperfield", 1891 (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
    - Graduation programs, 1891-1900 (Box 5, Folder 62-63)
    - Promotional booklet, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Report card of Charlie Starr, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - Blank report card, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Notice for summer and winter classes, 1891 (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Catalogue, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Printer image of alum J.P. Woodruff, undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Housatonic Valley Regional High School
    - Program for school dedication ceremony, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Newspaper article on school opening, , undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Booklet, "Housatonic Valley Regional High School: A Study in Regional Planning", 1941 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Annual report, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Article mentioning student Ernest H. Kenniston, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Program for 15th anniversary ceremony, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Newspaper with story about commencement, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - The Hotchkiss School
    - The Hotchkiss Bulletin, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Marvelwood School
    - School newsletter, The Blue and White, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Morris Academy
    - Article in The Morris Herald, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Rumsey Hall
    - Annual booklets, 1910-1936 (Box 6, Folder 4-14)
    - Issues of The Echo, 1906-1927 (Box 6, Folder 15-26)
    - Invitation to commencement, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Graduation weekend schedule, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Photograph catalogue, undated (Box 6, Folder 29-30)
    - Receipts of Edward D. Cartwright from Rumsey Hall Athletic Association, 1926-1928 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Commencement programs, 1907-1937 (Box 7, Folder 1-24)
  - The Taft School
    - Program for Christmas pageant, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - The Young Ladies’ Institute
    - Information on school, also known as the "Birds Nest", undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
- Colleges and Universities
  - Information regarding State Normal School summer session, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Constitution and by-laws of the Yale College Gamma Nu Society, 1875 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - The Laws of Yale College, 1877 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - The Yale Banner, 1880 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Yale College booklets and pamphlets, 1882-1909; , undated (Box 7, Folder 31-41)
  - Letter to alumni about Yale College corporation, 1886 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Commencement program, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 43)
- Miscellaneous
  - Connecticut state education laws, 1872 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Article, “Education, New and Old,” in Andover Review, 1886 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Columbus Day celebration message to public school children, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Connecticut School Document No. IX, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Report of the Congregational Educational Society, 1897 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Editorials by William D. Bosler, regarding poor state of Cornwall schools, 1899-1900 (Box 8, Folder 6-9)
  - Agents’ report regarding Southern educational requirements, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Negro Common School social study, 1901 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Report card of Ethel Oliver, 1903 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - "Connecticut School Register", 1909 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Programs for state Board of Education meetings at Grange Hall, 1912-1920 (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
  - Contest announcement of the Conn. Society of Colonial Dames, for students, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Sewing class notebook of E.A. Clark, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Memoranda about the cost of Cornwall students attending high school in other towns, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Program for state Board of Education meeting held in Cornwall, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Cornwall public schools closing exercises, 1926 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Report card of Lydia Hubbard, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - "George Washington: The Builder of the Nation", 1932 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - "The Mother of George Washington", 1932 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Marion Blake’s type-writing certificate from Litchfield High School, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - List of charter members of Cornwall P.T.A., undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - List of Cornwall donors for music education, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Old school card with geography statistics, undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - "Supplementary Reading for Primary Grades", undated (Box 8, Folder 28)